A Guide to the Papers of Collins Denny 1872-1943
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- Collins Denny Collection: Subdivided topically into Methodist Collection; Civil War and Reconstruction; and Miscellaneous
  - Protest literature 1916 (Box-folder 82:28)
    re: mission work in Mexico
  - Minutes of Mexican Conference 1916 (Box-folder 1916)
  - Report of investigation at Ruth Hargrove Institute 1916 (Box-folder 82:30)
  - Census form 1916 (Box-folder 82:31)
  - Minutes of annual Conference 1916 & 1917 (Box-folder 82:32)
  - Report of committees on Estimates Board of Missions 1917 (Box-folder 82:33)
  - Address of Bishop E. E. Hoss to General Conference 1918 (Box-folder 82:34)
  - Poem at Unveiling of Bust of W. A. Candler 1918 (Box-folder 82:35)
  - Synopsis of Council proceedings, African Methodist Church 1919 (Box-folder 82:36)
  - Minutes of Francis Ashbury Memorial Association 1922 (Box-folder 82:37)
  - The Ashbury Tablet 1922 (Box-folder 82:38)
  - Digest of Information on Nineteenth General Conference 1922 (Box-folder 82:39)
  - Mary Culler White and W. W. Pinson Correspondence 1923 (Box-folder 82:40)
  - Testimony in Chas. D. McGehee vs. Bishop W. F. McMurry Case1923 (Box-folder 82:41)
  - Report of Committee of Investigation on the case of Rev. T. P. Jimison 1924 (Box-folder 83:1)
  - Digest on General Conference 1926 (Box-folder 83:2)
  - "Methodism-Her Past and Future", Bob Shuler's Magazine 1926 (Box-folder 83:3)
  - Committee Hearings: Trial of Walter A. Kearn 1927 (Box-folder 83:4)
  - Lausanne, [Switzerland] Programme 1927 (Box-folder 83:5)
  - Articles on Randolph Macon College controversy 1928 (Box-folder 83:6)
  - Digest of General Conference 1930 (Box-folder 83:7)
  - re: Bishop Cannon Case n.d. (Box-folder 83:8)
  - Digest of General Conference 1934 (Box-folder 83:9)
  - Episcopal address of Bishop John M. Moore 1934 (Box-folder 83:10)
  - "Plan of Union.. ." 1935 (Box-folder 83:11)
  - "Northern Methodist Views on the Race Problem" Broadside 1937 April (Box-folder 83:12)
  - Digest of General Conference 1938 (Box-folder 83:13)
  - Birmingham (Ala.) Conference 1938 April. (Box-folder 83:14)
  - Unification literature 1924-1925 and n.d. (Box-folder 83:15)
  - Unification literature 1924-1925 and n.d. (Box-folder 83:16)
  - Unification literature n.d. (Box-folder 83:17)
  - Editorial 1938 March (Box-folder 83:18)
  - Resolutions against Unification 1938 (Box-folder 83:19)
  - Open letters from Layman's Organizations for Preservation of the Southern Methodist Church 1938-1939 (Box-folder 83:20)
  - Bulletins and Press Releases of Layman's Organizations for Preservation of the Southern Methodist Church 1938-1939 (Box-folder 83:21)
  - Copies of The Southern Methodist Layman 1938-1939 (Box-folder 84:1)
  - Delegate List at ? Conference [1938 or 1939?] (Box-folder 84:2)
  - Dan E. Turbeville vs. M. J. Morris 1940 January (Box-folder 84:3)
  - Minutes of meeting n.d. (Box-folder 84:4)
    re: Theological Seminary in Mexico
  - Statement n.d. (Box-folder 84:5)
    re: Oklahoma City University
  - Photo of site of Keywood House n.d. (Box-folder 84:6)
  - Statement on Ecclesiastical Courts n.d. (Box-folder 84:7)
  - "A Brief Account of the Division of the Methodist Episcopal in 1844 and.. ." by W. F. Glenn n.d. (Box-folder 84:8)
  - "Lost Identity" by A. H. Williams n.d. (Box-folder 84:9)
  - "Plain Reasons for an Important Change" by G. F. Smith n.d. (Box-folder 84:10)
  - A list of books for young Preachers n.d. (Box-folder 84:11)
  - The Order for the Adminstration of Baptism n.d. (Box-folder 84:12)
  - Church picture on post cards n.d. (Box-folder 84:13)
  - Miscellaneous Programs, etc. n.d. (Box-folder 84:14)
  - "Storming Cemeterey Hill" by Thomas D. Houston 1882 (Box-folder 84:15)
  - History of Facts of the Great Naval Battle Between The Merrimac and The Monitor 1908 (Box-folder 84:16)
  - Tributes to Robert E. Lee 1913 (Box-folder 84:17)
  - "The Wilderness Campaign" and "The Battles of Fredericksburg and Chancellorsville, Va." by V. M. Flemming 1921 and 1922 (Box-folder 84:18)
  - "Just Before and After Lee Surrendered to Grant" by Giles B. Cooke 1922 (Box-folder 84:19)
  - "The Story of Old Star Fort" 1923 October (Box-folder 84:20)
  - Copy of Lee's Farewell Address [Recieved 1924?] (Box-folder 84:21)
  - Economic Factors in the Manufacture of Confederate Ordinance 1925 December (Box-folder 84:22)
  - Articles on Civil War received 1922-1926 (Box-folder 84:23)
  - Miss Rutherford's Historical Notes on Lincoln and Davis 1927 (Box-folder 84:24)
  - "Robert E. Lee; Is His Military Genius Fact or Fiction?" 1928 (Box-folder 84:25)
  - Character sketches of Robert E. Lee, Jefferson Davis, and Stonewall Jackson by H. H. Smith n.d. (Box-folder 84:26)
  - History of the Seige of Vicksburg n.d. (Box-folder 84:27)
  - Map of Mechanicsville, Cold Harbor and North Anna Battlefields n.d. (Box-folder 84:28)
  - "The Legend of Captain James McCarthy" n.d. (Box-folder 84:29)
  - Photo of South Carolina Legislature of 1868 1868 (Box-folder 84:30)
  - Letters recommending E. J. Halle for Foreign Service--printed by State Department 1885 and 1893 (Box-folder 84:31)
  - "The Possibility of Miracles" 1906 (Box-folder 84:32)
  - "The Bible and Progress" by Woodrow Wilson 1911 May (Box-folder 84:33)
  - "Woodrow Wilson" by Dr. Edwin A. Alderman 1912 (Box-folder 84:34)
  - Far East Cruise Advertisement 1912 (Box-folder 84:35)
  - Translation of certain sections of the New Mexican Constitution 1917 (Box-folder 84:36)
  - A Quinqennial Resume of the The National Bank of Commerce of Baltimore 1878-1917 (Box-folder 84:37)
  - Carnegie Foundation List of Publications 1918 (Box-folder 84:38)
  - "The United States Leads The World in Divorce by Joseph E. Ransdell 1922 (Box-folder 84:39)
  - "The University Commission on Southern Race Questions" by Josiah Morse 1920 October (Box-folder 84:40)
  - Excerpt of Congressional Record on 14th and 15rh Amendments 1928 January (Box-folder 84:41)
  - "The Yorktown Book" 1931 (Box-folder 84:42)
  - Manuscript from Seagle Papers n.d. (Box-folder 84:43)
  - Copy of Will of C. M. Gentry 1922 (Box-folder 84:44)
  - Petition for Appeal 1922 (Box-folder 84:45)
  - World Court Congress Announcement n.d. (Box-folder 84:46)
  - Memorandum on Officer's Training Schools n.d. (Box-folder 84:47)
  - Paper on "Spirit Communication" n.d. (Box-folder 84:48)
  - Miscellaneous advertisments, etc. n.d. (Box-folder 84:49)
  - 2 Speeches and commentary; "The Statue of the Negro" n.d. (Box-folder 85:1)
  - Annual Fiscal Report of the Board of Extension of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South n.d. (Box-folder 85:2)
  - Statements and Reports of the Book Committee and Book Agents of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South n.d. (Box-folder 85:3)
  - Materials n.d. (Box-folder 85:4)
    re: China Publishing House
  - Miscellaneous Reports, Methodist Episcopal Church, South n.d. (Box-folder 85:5)
  - Miscellaneous Articles n.d. (Box-folder 85:6)
    re: Methodism
  - Deed to Epworth University n.d. (Box-folder 85:7)
- Denny and Collins Family Papers
  - Receipts and notes 1868-1905 (Box-folder 86:1)
  - Certificates; Hiram Masonic Lodge #21, Winchester, Virginia 1867 and 1885 (Box-folder 86:2)
  - William R. Denny and Masonic Lodge #21, Winchester, Virginia 1868,1878 and n.d. (Box-folder 86:3)
  - William R. Denny: Tax list 1876-1895 (Box-folder 86:4)
  - William R. Denny: Speech to Masonic Lodge #21, Winchester, Virginia [188?] (Box-folder 86:5)
  - Power of Attorney and letters 1868-1889 (Box-folder 86:6)
    re: Merger of Winchester & Potomac R. R. Co. and Balimore & Ohio
  - William R. Denny: Stockholders Report of Winchester & Potomac R. R. Co. 1889 October (Box-folder 86:7)
  - Winchester & Potomac R. R. vs. U. S. 1889 (Box-folder 86:8)
  - William R. Denny: Partnership agreements 1891 December (Box-folder 86:9)
  - William R. Denny: Cash Book of Denny Bros., San Marcos, Texas 1891 (Box-folder 86:10)
  - Law suits of Denny Bros. in Tenn. and Texas Courts 1897 (Box-folder 86:11)
  - William R. Denny: Personal account books and check stubs 1892-1897 (Box-folder 86:12)
  - William R. Denny: Account book with Shenandoah Valley National Bank, Winchester, Va. 1892-1902 (Box-folder 86:13)
  - Settlement of the Estate of William R. Denny 1904-1913 (Box-folder 86:14)
  - Map, William R. Denny's subdivision of lots n.d. (Box-folder 86:15)
  - William R. Denny: Courts order in William R. Denny vs. James L. Giles case n.d. (Box-folder 86:16)
  - William R. Denny: Architectural drawings n.d. (Box-folder 86:17)
  - William R. Denny: News clippings 86:18 (Box-folder 86:18)
  - William R. Denny: Photographs n.d. (Box-folder 86:19)
  - Williams R. Denny: Poetry n.d. (Box-folder 86:20)
  - William R. Denny: Calling card plate n.d. (Box-folder 86:21)
  - William R. Denny: Memorabilia 1870-1874 (Box-folder 86:22)
  - Joseph S. Collins: Lock of hair 1874 (Box-folder 86:23)
  - Joseph S. Collins: News clippings of obiturary 86:24 (Box-folder 86:24)
  - John A. Collins: Letter to Editor of Religious Herald on Immersion and Methodist Episcopal Church 1834 December (Box-folder 86:25)
  - John A. Collins: Speech on Slaveholding and Methodist Episcopal Church Membership 1856 June (Box-folder 86:26)
  - John A. Collins: Speech on "Conference Rights" n.d. (Box-folder 87:1)
  - John A. Collins: Speech and articles n.d. (Box-folder 87:2)
    re: Lay Delegations and the General Conference
  - John A. Collins: "The Rights of the Laity of the Methodist Episcopal Church" n.d. (Box-folder 87:3)
  - John A. Collins: Speech on Baltimore Conference, Slavery and Abolitionism n.d. (Box-folder 87:4)
  - John A. Collins: Speeches on Methodist Episcopal Church and Slavery n.d. (Box-folder 87:5)
  - John A. Collins: Speeches [American Colonization Society?] on Africa and Libera n.d. (Box-folder 87:6)
  - John A. Collins: Speech on Intemperance, President [Dublin?] n.d. (Box-folder 87:7)
  - John A. Collins: Speech [of invitation to.. .]... Dickinson College n.d. (Box-folder 87:8)
  - John A. Collins: Speech n.d. (Box-folder 87:9)
    re: Dickinson College
  - John A. Collins: Speech notes at Methodist Conference n.d. (Box-folder 87:10)
  - John A. Collins: Speech in behalf of the Seamen's Bethel Union, Baltimore n.d. (Box-folder 87:11)
  - John A. Collins: Eulogy on Andrew Jackson n.d. (Box-folder 87:12)
  - John A. Collins: Eulogy on William Henry Harrison n.d. (Box-folder 87:13)
  - John A. Collins: Petition against dueling n.d. (Box-folder 87:14)
  - John A. Collins: Speeches and speech fragments n.d. (Box-folder 87:15)
  - John A. Collins: Sermon notes n.d. (Box-folder 87:16)
  - John Henry Denny: Grade reports from Winchester schools 1877 (Box-folder 87:17)
  - John Henry Denny: News clippings 1800-1901 (Box-folder 87:18)
    re: his death in Phillipines
  - John Henry Denny: Certificate of appointment as Quartermaster Sergeant 1898 (Box-folder 87:19)
  - Joseph Benson Collins: Obituary clippings n.d. (Box-folder 87:20)
  - Caroline Collins: Obituary clippings n.d. (Box-folder 87:21)
  - James W. Denny: Property listing 1916 December (Box-folder 87:22)
  - James W. Denny: News clippings on Congressional candidacy 87:23 (Box-folder 87:23)
  - Will of James W. Denny 87:24 (Box-folder 87:24)
  - Report of Lucy Chase Denny from Randolph-Macon Woman's College 1912 (Box-folder 87:25)
  - Lucy Chapman Denny: Shakespeare [notes] for speech to [V. U. Woman's Club] n.d. (Box-folder 87:26)
  - Religious literature originally belonging to Lucy and Anna Denny n.d. (Box-folder 87:27)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Article "The Honor System's Place in Preparatory Schools" 1917 (Box-folder 87:28)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Debate "American vs. English Cabinet System" 1917 (Box-folder 87:29)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Speech notes, "Carlyle's Essay on Burns" n.d. (Box-folder 87:30)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Speech notes, "Burke's Speech on Conciliation" n.d. (Box-folder 87:31)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Lecture notes, "Labor Problems" n.d. (Box-folder 87:32)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Reports from Chamberlayne School 1912-1917 (Box-folder 87:33)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Chamberlayne School Publication and Roll 1915-1916 (Box-folder 87:34)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Physical Report, The Mercersburg Academy 1916 (Box-folder 87:35)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Mercerburg Academy Declamation Contest 1917 May (Box-folder 87:36)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Mercerburg Academy Annual Commencement Program 1917 May (Box-folder 87:37)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: College Entrance Examination Scores n.d. (Box-folder 87:38)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.; Princeton University Report 1918 June (Box-folder 87:39)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Draft Board Classification Card 1918 (Box-folder 87:40)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Pay vouchers as 2nd Lieut., U. S. Army 1918 (Box-folder 87:41)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Furlough certificates and memo to Platoon Leaders 1918 (Box-folder 87:42)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Insurance certificates, U. S. Army 1918 (Box-folder 87:43)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Graduation Program of University of Virginia, law degree 1924 (Box-folder 87:44)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Letter to Editor, Richmond Times Dispatch 1938 April 13 (Box-folder 87:45)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: News clippings 1916 (Box-folder 87:46)
    re: Mercerburg Academy Football
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: News clippings; Mercerburg Academy Debate 1917 March (Box-folder 87:47)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.: Graduation news clippings from Mercersburg Academy 1917 June (Box-folder 87:48)
  - Collins Denny, Jr.; New clippings 1914 and n.d. (Box-folder 87:49)
  - Lucy Denny (Slosson): Master Thesis, "The Virginia Military District in Ohio" 1932 (Box-folder 87:50)
  - Denny Family: Cards n.d. (Box-folder 87:51)
  - Report of Wesleyan Female Institute 1896 (Box-folder 88:1)
  - Empty envelopes n.d. (Box-folder 88:2)
  - Miscellaneous maps 88:3 (Box-folder 88:3)
  - Miscellaneous n.d. (Box-folder 88:4)
  - Miscellaneous photos n.d. (Box-folder 88:5)
  - Blank presiding elder certificates n.d. (Box-folder 88:6)
- Items added later
  - re: Methodist Church, including list of ministers and appropriations for missions ca. 1914-1930, 25 items (Box-folder 2672-b)
  - Letters, mostly invitations 1894-1906, 12 letters (Box-folder 2672-c)
  - Charles S. Stanton to Collins Denny 1897 August- September, 3 TLs (Box-folder 2672-c)
    re: history of Strawbridge and Sam's Creek Churches
  - Jordan Stokes to Collins Denny, 1898 May 12, TLs (Box-folder 2672-c)
    re: General Conference accepting money from Congress
  - Letters of application and recommendation for M. W. Swartz, of the University of Virginia, to become instructor of Latin at Vanderbilt University 1900 April, 5 items (Box-folder 2672-c)
  - R. P. Wilson to Collins Denny 1904 January, 2 TLS (Box-folder 2672-c)
    re: affairs of Methodist Publishing House in China
  - 5 items, including 2 examination papers, in Deductive Logic by W. E. Douglas, Vanderbilt, University 1879 May- June (Box-folder 2672-d)
  - 3 items, including 2 TLs, from S. Galeski, Supreme Secretary of the American Guild 1903 May (Box-folder 2672-d)
  - Folio #1
    - "Track Chart of the World" published by the Admiralty, showing route of Bishop Denny's Trip Around the World, (1886] 1874 January 21, oversize
    - [Section of map of Shanghai District, China Conference, Methodist Episcopal Church, South] [1886], 3 copies; oversize
    - Map of Shanghai District, China Conference, Methodist Episcopal Church, South 1886, 7 copies; oversize
    - [Chinese Chess Board] n.d., oversize
    - 4 Photographs n.d., oversize
  - Folio #2
    - Bishop of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South 1925 May, oversize
    - The Reverand John Wesley preaching in the Gwennad Amphitheatre n.d., oversize
    - Baltimore Conference, [Delegate pictures?] 1893, oversize
    - Newspaper articles on Espicopalian Homecoming n.d., oversize
    - Newspaper article "Arlington is Rich in Historical Atmosphere" n.d., oversize
    - Newspaper article "Woodlawn- Washington's Gift" n.d., oversize
    - Newspaper article "Tulip Hill-A Mansion of Dreams" n.d., oversize
    - Assorted newspaper clippings from Richmond Time Dispatch ca. 1931, 3 sheets; oversize
    - Dog Portrait, "Who said Rats' " n.d., oversize
    - Bishops of the Episcopal Church, South 1852, oversize